<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Posts on  </title>
    <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <author>Ross Lawley</author>
    <rights>Copyright (c) 2013, Ross Lawley; all rights reserved.</rights>
    <updated>2014-04-23 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to: Handle multiple Scala versions</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/how-to-handle-multiple-scala-versions</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/how-to-handle-multiple-scala-versions</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently upgraded &lt;a href=&#34;http://mongodb.github.io/casbah/&#34;&gt;Casbah&lt;/a&gt; to support the latest Scala 2.11 release and for the first time when supporting multiple Scala versions I hit a stumbling block.  If you&amp;rsquo;re writing a library that wants to support multiple versions of Scala in a single code base, it&amp;rsquo;s generally easy isn&amp;rsquo;t it? Thankfully, it is as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scala-sbt.org/&#34;&gt;sbt&lt;/a&gt; can do the heavy lifting for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Three steps to success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sbt documentation covers the basics nicely in their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scala-sbt.org/release/docs/Detailed-Topics/Cross-Build.html&#34;&gt;cross build&lt;/a&gt; documentation.  But what&amp;rsquo;s the path to success?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choose the Scala&amp;rsquo;s you are going to support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set the &lt;code&gt;crossScalaVersions&lt;/code&gt; setting in your build file to define the Scala versions you want to support. In Casbah we support: &lt;code&gt;crossScalaVersions := Seq(&amp;quot;2.11.0&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;2.10.4&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;2.9.3&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Configure libraries&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it can get hairy because third party libraries may not support all your favoured scala builds in their latest release.  If they do, then happy days but if not you may have to pick out each library version as needed.  Here is an example from the Casbah build:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// In the build settings append to the library dependencies
libraryDependencies &amp;lt;++= scalaVersion (sv =&amp;gt; Seq(specs2(sv), scalatime(sv)))


// Helper method to pattern match against the scala version and return the correct specs version
def specs2(scalaVersion: String) =
  (scalaVersion match {
    case &amp;quot;2.9.3&amp;quot;   =&amp;gt; &amp;quot;org.specs2&amp;quot; %% &amp;quot;specs2&amp;quot; % &amp;quot;1.12.4.1&amp;quot;
    case _ =&amp;gt; &amp;quot;org.specs2&amp;quot; %% &amp;quot;specs2&amp;quot; % &amp;quot;2.3.11&amp;quot;
  }) % &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the latest Specs build &lt;code&gt;2.3.11&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t support Scala 2.9.3 we have to use the older &lt;code&gt;1.12.4.1&lt;/code&gt; version for 2.9.3.  The downside is we can&amp;rsquo;t yet use some of the nicer newer features of the Specs library in our test suite.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scala version specific code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the real challenge, what do you do if you need specific code for a specific version of Scala?  Hopefully, you&amp;rsquo;ll never need to but this isn&amp;rsquo;t always the case as I found with Casbah.  We use &lt;code&gt;BeanInfo&lt;/code&gt; annotation and it lives in &lt;code&gt;scala.reflection&lt;/code&gt; in Scala 2.9.3 and in &lt;code&gt;scala.beans&lt;/code&gt; in 2.11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we get round this? Luckily, Scala 2.10 gave me a hint as &lt;code&gt;BeanInfo&lt;/code&gt; had been depreciated in &lt;code&gt;scala.reflection&lt;/code&gt; but they had mirrored it in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/scala/scala/blob/v2.10.4/src/library/scala/reflect/package.scala#L55-L56&#34;&gt;package object&lt;/a&gt;. I could use the same trick in Casbah! However, I would need a version for Scala 2.9.3 to point to &lt;code&gt;scala.reflect.BeanInfo&lt;/code&gt; and a version for 2.10 &amp;amp; 2.11. Then update all the code to point to the scala specific package object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the code would be version specific it couldn&amp;rsquo;t live in the &lt;code&gt;src/main/scala&lt;/code&gt; directory as it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t compile. So instead I created specific Scala directories in &lt;code&gt;src/main&lt;/code&gt; like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./scala
./scala_2.9.3  // Scala 2.9.3 specific code
./scala_2.10   // Scala 2.10 specific code
./scala_2.11   // Scala 2.11 specific code
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Scala 2.10 &amp;amp; 2.11 point versions will be binary compatible I only need a top level directory for them.  Then alls that&amp;rsquo;s needed is to add these source directories to the build:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;unmanagedSourceDirectories in Compile &amp;lt;+= (sourceDirectory in Compile, scalaBinaryVersion){
  (s, v) =&amp;gt; s / (&amp;quot;scala_&amp;quot;+v)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds extra source directories to the compile step and using &lt;code&gt;scalaBinaryVersion&lt;/code&gt; I get the binary compatible versions (so it&amp;rsquo;s 2.11 for all 2.11 releases but would be 2.9.3, 2.9.2, 2.9.1 for the non compatible point releases from the 2.9 series).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fix in Casbah was to simply add a &lt;code&gt;beans.scala&lt;/code&gt; for the scala specific versions and create a &lt;code&gt;BeanInfo&lt;/code&gt; type which points to the correct scala package. Problem solved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sbt allow you to run any command against multiple versions of Scala. &lt;code&gt;./sbt +test&lt;/code&gt; will test against all your &lt;code&gt;crossScalaVersions&lt;/code&gt; of Scala and hopefully confirm the code works as expected.  If I want to test a specific version use a double plus sign and add the version string to the arguments eg: &lt;code&gt;./sbt ++ 2.9.3 test&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scala is a relatively fast moving ecosystem with new major releases every 13 months or so.  When I took over Casbah it supported 6 binary incompatible versions of Scala! From 2.8.1 to 2.9.3. Happily, Scala patch versions from 2.10.0 on have become binary compatible making supporting multiple versions of Scala easier.  However, one of the key issues for maintaining a library is to know when to end of life an old Scala version, so to keep the library fresh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Casbah supporting the current and last major versions of Scala gives users support for the latest MongoDB version and allows them some flexibility when it comes to updating Scala. Generally, this has been a trouble free process and as shown above problems are solvable in just three easy steps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RxJava - understandably reactive</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/rx-java</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/rx-java</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Reactive programing is hot stuff at the moment and the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/reactive&#34;&gt;Coursera Principles of Reactive Programming&lt;/a&gt;
course has &lt;strong&gt;just&lt;/strong&gt; started (its not too late to enroll).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been hearing good things about &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Netflix/RxJava&#34;&gt;RxJava&lt;/a&gt; (
a port of .Net&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-gb/data/gg577609.aspx&#34;&gt;Reactive extensions&lt;/a&gt;
) so I wanted to learn some more. Then I stumbled upon a video from a recent
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/SF-Scala/&#34;&gt;SF Scala&lt;/a&gt; meetup
which covered what it is and how they implemented the core and then added
support for other JVM languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things immediately struck me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Observables are not opnionated about how the backend works.  It could be
concurrent or swapped out with a thread pool, an actor
or an nio event &amp;amp; event loop&amp;hellip; Pretty cool, this means there is a single way
of handling the code no matter if the backend is synchronus or asynchronus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The methods for manipulating multiple observers, chaining or nesting
is extremely powerful, yet easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m really looking forward to using it, to me its an easier abstraction to
understand for handling streams of data and seemly less complex than using Plays
excellent &lt;code&gt;Iteratee.Concurrent&lt;/code&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;embed video-player&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&#34;youtube-player&#34; type=&#34;text/html&#34;
    width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34;
    src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/tOMK_FYJREw&#34;
    allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Typesafe&#39;s Activator</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/typesafe_activator</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/typesafe_activator</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the &lt;a href=&#34;http://typesafe.com/blog/announcing-activator-10-create-reactive-apps-in-minutes&#34;&gt;Typesafe Activator&lt;/a&gt;
hit 1.0. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t heard about it and use scala or the jvm then take five
minutes and check it out - its worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;What is it?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My recommendation alone not enough and you what to know more about it before
installing it?  No problems, let me convince you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typesafe Activator is a local web &amp;amp; command-line tool that helps developers
get started with the Typesafe Platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whats that give you?  Basically, a real nice UI in the browser for creating web
applications from templates.  The &lt;a href=&#34;http://typesafe.com/activator/templates&#34;&gt;templates&lt;/a&gt;
cover &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; in scala to using &lt;a href=&#34;http://akka.io&#34;&gt;Akka&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://playframework.com&#34;&gt;
Play&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scala-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; to create
modern scalable reactive web sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its quick and easy to get going - I chose the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://typesafe.com/activator/template/play-mongo-knockout&#34;&gt;Play Reactive Mongo and knockout.js&lt;/a&gt;
template&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;text-center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/images/activator-loading.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the background it downloads all the resources you need to create the project
from the template.  Starting a new project is extremely simple and once the
project is loaded you get to use the Web UI in anger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;text-center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/images/activator-orientation.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;The tutorial&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once loaded, you get the tutorial for this template:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is going reactive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, response times in the seconds were considered appropriate. Browser
refreshes were the norm in web applications. Systems would go down for hours of
maintenance, or even be rebooted nightly, and this was ok because people only
expected the systems to be up during business hours..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exciting stuff!&lt;/em&gt;  So not only can you code, compile and test your application
all in the browser - there&amp;rsquo;s a tutorial to guide you through the various new
concepts as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reactive mongo tutorial, gets you up and running using creating a reactive
Play web application with a rich front end and scalable backend.  It uses
&lt;a href=&#34;http://reactivemongo.org&#34;&gt;Reactive Mongo&lt;/a&gt; an asynchronous non blocking scala
mongodb driver for the database.  The play framework for the webserver,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://coffeescript.org&#34;&gt;coffeescript&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://knockoutjs.com&#34;&gt;knockout.js&lt;/a&gt;
for the frontend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tutorial walks you through how the various parts of the app work together and
links through to the code.  Next it sets tasks to update parts of the app, extending
it and adding functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quickly, gets you up to speed, so if you are interested in any of the
Typesafe stack then download activator now and you&amp;rsquo;ll be up and running in minutes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Sublime Text 3</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/switching-to-sublimetext-3</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/switching-to-sublimetext-3</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For a long while I&amp;rsquo;ve been a huge fan of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sublimetext.com/&#34;&gt;Sublime Text 2&lt;/a&gt;,
its easy to use and has a wealth of features that can be installed by the
awesome &lt;a href=&#34;http://wbond.net/sublime_packages/package_control&#34;&gt;package control&lt;/a&gt;
system. I use it for all python development and any adhoc file work, infact I
only abandon it for my scala work - where IntelliJ wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sublime Text 3 (ST3) has been in beta for six months, and over that time its
plugin ecosystem has matured.  After experiencing some slow downs in
Sublime Text 2 (ST2) I thought it was time to upgrade to an even more
sublime experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;5 step migration to Sublime Text 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off there is &lt;strong&gt;no risk&lt;/strong&gt; in trying to upgrade, it has a different app
name to ST2 and its configurations are in a different directory. In short you
can have both installed and living happily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;1. Can I upgrade?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goto the awesome &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caniswitchtosublimetext3.com/&#34;&gt;Can I Switch To Sublime Text 3?&lt;/a&gt;
website and check your packages.  Its probably not a goer if your most used
plugin doesn&amp;rsquo;t work in ST3, but do check out alternatives as many packages
have already been updated and do now work with ST3.  My results were as
follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;text-center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/images/ready_for_sublime.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had one fail but when looking at the package reposititory it suggested an
ST3 alternative for a python code intel tool that would work (SublimeJEDI) -
so I was good to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;2. Install package control and packages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its easy to install package control, just checkout the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wbond.net/sublime_packages/package_control/installation#ST3&#34;&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt;.
Once installed, open package control and install all the green packages
mentioned on the can I switch website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be tempted to use package control for the yellow packages - as it will
install the ST2 versions which won&amp;rsquo;t work.  Instead you will need to
manually install - this usually is simple and only involves cloning the
plugin repository into your packages directory and then checking out an
ST3 compatible branch.  Its no real hardship - so go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;3. Migrate settings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all the packages are installed, its time to get ST3 as comfy as you had
ST2.  To do this copy and paste your user settings from:
&lt;code&gt;Preferences -&amp;gt; Settings -&amp;gt; User&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then copy any language specific settings and snippets you have from the User
directory of ST2 into the User directory of ST3 eg:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cp ~/Library/Application\ Support/Sublime\ Text\ 2/Packages/User/Python.sublime-settings ~/Library/Application\ Support/Sublime\ Text\ 3/Packages/User/Python.sublime-settings
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;4. Update the subl helper:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remove / rename any symlinked helpers then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo ln -s &amp;quot;/Applications/Sublime Text.app/Contents/SharedSupport/bin/subl&amp;quot; /usr/bin/subl
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;5. Profit!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy eh?  You now have ST3 configured as you are used to and if anything
is buggy (&lt;em&gt;it is still in a beta&lt;/em&gt;) you can easily switch back to ST2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial impressions are its &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;much faster&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and I haven&amp;rsquo;t hit any bugs yet,
so I&amp;rsquo;m a happy bunny. But if you need more convincing - heres some extra reasons
to make the switch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speed.
Startup time, file load time, and Replace All have all been
significantly improved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improved Project and Pane management.
Working with multiple panes is now more efficient, with commands to
create and destroy panes, and quickly move files between panes.  Also
you can now have multiple workspaces per project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Better Symbol Indexing.
Allows goto definitions and goto symbol in a project, as well as new
jump forward and jump back features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need some more reasons? Check out the original
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sublimetext.com/blog/articles/sublime-text-3-beta&#34;&gt;Sublime Text 3 announcement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you are on Sublime Text 2 then download Sublime Text 3 and see if
you can make the switch today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using MongoDB to find the most popular pub names!</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/the-most-popular-pub-name</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/the-most-popular-pub-name</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the year I gave a talk at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.10gen.com/events/mongodb-london-2013&#34;&gt;MongoDB London&lt;/a&gt;
about the different aggregation options with MongoDB.  The topic recently came up again
in conversation at a user group, so I thought it deserved a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Gathering ideas for the talk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to give a more interesting aggregation talk than the standard
&amp;ldquo;counting words in text&amp;rdquo;, and as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.mongodb.org/manual/core/aggregation/&#34;&gt;aggregation framework&lt;/a&gt; gained shiny &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.mongodb.org/manual/core/2dsphere/&#34;&gt;2dsphere geo&lt;/a&gt; support in
&lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.mongodb.org/manual/release-notes/2.4/#new-geospatial-indexes-with-geojson-and-improved-spherical-geometry&#34;&gt;2.4&lt;/a&gt;, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d use that. I just needed a topic&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;What are us Brits focused on?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things immediately sprang to mind: &lt;strong&gt;weather&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;beer&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opted to focus on something close to my heart: &lt;strong&gt;beer&lt;/strong&gt; :)
But what to aggregate about beer? Then I remembered an old pub quiz favourite&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the most popular pub name in the UK?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there is some great open data, including a wealth of information
on pubs available from the awesome &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openstreetmap.org/&#34;&gt;open street map&lt;/a&gt;
project.  I just need to get at it and happily the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.overpass-api.de&#34;&gt;Overpass-api&lt;/a&gt;
provides a simple &amp;ldquo;xapi&amp;rdquo; interface for OSM data.
All I needed was anything tagged with &lt;code&gt;amenity=pub&lt;/code&gt; within in the
bounds of the UK and with their xapi interface this is as simple as a wget:
&lt;code&gt;http://www.overpass-api.de/api/xapi?*[amenity=pub][bbox=-10.5,49.78,1.78,59]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had an osm file I used the &lt;a href=&#34;http://imposm.org/&#34;&gt;imposm python library&lt;/a&gt; to
parse the xml and then convert it to following GeoJSON format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;code class=&#34;javascript&#34;&gt;{
  &#34;_id&#34; : 451152,
  &#34;amenity&#34; : &#34;pub&#34;,
  &#34;name&#34; : &#34;The Dignity&#34;,
  &#34;addr:housenumber&#34; : &#34;363&#34;,
  &#34;addr:street&#34; : &#34;Regents Park Road&#34;,
  &#34;addr:city&#34; : &#34;London&#34;,
  &#34;addr:postcode&#34; : &#34;N3 1DH&#34;,
  &#34;toilets&#34; : &#34;yes&#34;,
  &#34;toilets:access&#34; : &#34;customers&#34;,
  &#34;location&#34; : {
      &#34;type&#34; : &#34;Point&#34;,
      &#34;coordinates&#34; : [-0.1945732, 51.6008172]
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it was a case of simply inserting it as a document into MongoDB. I
quickly noticed that the data needed a little cleaning, as I was seeing duplicate
pub names, for example: &amp;ldquo;The Red Lion&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Red Lion&amp;rdquo;.  Because I wanted to make
a wordle I normalised all the pub names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about the importing process, the full loading code is
available on github: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rozza/pubnames/blob/master/osm2mongo.py&#34;&gt;osm2mongo.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Top pub names&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out finding the most popular pub names is very simple with the
aggregation framework.  Just group by the name and then sum up all the occurrences.
To get the top five most popular pub names we sort by the summed value and then
limit to 5:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-md-6 col-lg-6&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;code class=&#34;javascript&#34;&gt;db.pubs.aggregate([
  {&#34;$group&#34;:
     {&#34;_id&#34;: &#34;$name&#34;,
      &#34;value&#34;: {&#34;$sum&#34;: 1}
     }
  },
  {&#34;$sort&#34;: {&#34;value&#34;: -1}},
  {&#34;$limit&#34;: 5}
]);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-md-6 col-lg-6&#34;&gt;
For the whole of the UK this returns:

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Red Lion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Royal Oak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Crown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The White Hart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The White Horse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;text-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/images/pubs_wordle.png&#34;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Top pub names near you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At MongoDB London I thought that was too easy, so filtered to find the top pub
names near the conference and showing off some of the geo functionality that became
available in MongoDB 2.4.  To limit the result set match and ensure the
location is within a 2 mile radius by using &lt;code&gt;$centreSphere&lt;/code&gt;. Just provide the
coordinates &lt;code&gt;[ &amp;lt;long&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;lat&amp;gt; ]&lt;/code&gt; and a radius of roughly 2 miles
(3959 is approximately the radius of the earth, so divide it by 2):
&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;code class=&#34;javascript&#34;&gt;db.pubs.aggregate([
    { &amp;ldquo;$match&amp;rdquo; : { &amp;ldquo;location&amp;rdquo;:
                 { &amp;ldquo;$within&amp;rdquo;:
                   { &amp;ldquo;$text-centerSphere&amp;rdquo;: [[-0.12, 51.516], 2 / 3959] }}}
    },
    { &amp;ldquo;$group&amp;rdquo; :
       { &amp;ldquo;_id&amp;rdquo; : &amp;ldquo;$name&amp;rdquo;,
         &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; : { &amp;ldquo;$sum&amp;rdquo; : 1 } }
    },
    { &amp;ldquo;$sort&amp;rdquo; : { &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; : -1 } },
    { &amp;ldquo;$limit&amp;rdquo; : 5 }
  ]);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;What about where I live?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the conference I looked the most popular pub name near the conference.  Thats
great if you happen to live in the centre of London but what about everyone else
in the UK? So for this blog post I decided to update the demo code and make it
dynamic based on where you live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a href=&#34;http://pubnames.rosslawley.co.uk&#34;&gt;pubnames.rosslawley.co.uk&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;(It may take
some time for the heroku dyno to wake, so please be patient!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologies for those outside the UK - the demo app doesn&amp;rsquo;t have data for the
whole world - its surely possible to do, I just lacked the patience to download
it all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Cheers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;text-center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/images/almurray.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Original image: http://www.flickr.com/photos/bradfordtheatres/3063899946&#34; /&gt; &lt;br&gt;
  &lt;small&gt; Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/bradfordtheatres/3063899946&#34;/&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/bradfordtheatres/3063899946&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the code is available in my repo on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rozza/pubnames&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;
including the bson file of the pubs and the wordle code - so fork it and start
playing with MongoDB&amp;rsquo;s great geo features!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mongoengine 0.8.0</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/mongoengine-0-dot-8-dot-0</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/mongoengine-0-dot-8-dot-0</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m really pleased to annouce the release of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/mongoengine/0.8.0&#34;&gt;MongoEngine 0.8.0&lt;/a&gt;.
Its been a &lt;em&gt;long process&lt;/em&gt; due to work and life commitments but the latest version
of MongoEngine is here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Whats changed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been loads of fixes, improvements and changes in 0.8.
The headliners are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum requirements are python 2.6+ and pymongo 2.5+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inheritance now off by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inherited documents store &lt;code&gt;_cls&lt;/code&gt; not &lt;code&gt;_types&lt;/code&gt; (preventing auto creation of
multikey indexes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Querysets are immutable and now return clones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Geo Fields supporting mongodb 2.4 new &amp;ldquo;2dSphere&amp;rdquo; indexes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New context managers for switching collections or databases on the fly as
well as turning off dereferencing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django support improved (now supports Django 1.5.1, groups and permissions)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance improvements, back to the same performance as 0.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And much, much more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the full &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.mongoengine.org/en/latest/changelog.html#changes-in-0-8-0&#34;&gt;changelog&lt;/a&gt;
for all changes or check &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MongoEngine/mongoengine/&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; to see the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MongoEngine/mongoengine/issues?milestone=2&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;state=closed&#34;&gt;96 tickets&lt;/a&gt;
that have been fixed as part of this release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Whats next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of ideas on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MongoEngine/mongoengine/issues?milestone=6&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; for 0.9.  I&amp;rsquo;m looking for people to help with the administration and coding
of MongoEngine, so please get involved and help drive MongoEngine forward!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoEngine 0.8 RC1 Released</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/mongoengine-0-dot-8-rc1-released</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/mongoengine-0-dot-8-rc1-released</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notice:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.8.0RC3 has been released fixing a couple of small bugs and extra improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notice:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.8.0RC2 has been released fixing an obscure queryset cursor cloning issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m really pleased to annouce the release candidate for &lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/mongoengine/0.8.0RC1&#34;&gt;MongoEngine 0.8&lt;/a&gt;!
Its been a &lt;em&gt;long process&lt;/em&gt; due to work and life commitments but the latest version
of MongoEngine is ready for testing and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Why a release candidate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been massive changes in the internals, requiring thought and
&lt;strong&gt;testing&lt;/strong&gt; before upgrading and releasing to the wild - so please
read the &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.mongoengine.org/en/latest/upgrade.html#to-0-8&#34;&gt;upgrade&lt;/a&gt;
docs carefully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes are worth it and make using &lt;a href=&#34;http://mongoengine.org&#34;&gt;MongoEngine&lt;/a&gt;
even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please test 0.8.0RC1 on your test systems and staging systems and any feedback
please email the &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/group/mongoengine-users&#34;&gt;user group&lt;/a&gt;
or if you&amp;rsquo;d prefer to message me directly you can via
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rozza&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rozza&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Whats changed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been loads of fixes, improvements and changes in 0.8.
The headliners are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum requirements are python 2.6+ and pymongo 2.5+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inheritance now off by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inherited documents store &lt;code&gt;_cls&lt;/code&gt; not &lt;code&gt;_types&lt;/code&gt; (preventing auto creation of
multikey indexes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Querysets are immutable and now return clones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Geo Fields supporting mongodb 2.4 new &amp;ldquo;2dSphere&amp;rdquo; indexes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New context managers for switching collections or databases on the fly as
well as turning off dereferencing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django support improved (now supports Django 1.5.1, groups and permissions)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance improvements, back to the same performance as 0.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And much, much more! See the full &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.mongoengine.org/en/latest/changelog.html#changes-in-0-8-0&#34;&gt;changelog&lt;/a&gt;
for all changes or check &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MongoEngine/mongoengine/&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; to see the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MongoEngine/mongoengine/issues?milestone=2&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;state=closed&#34;&gt;84 tickets&lt;/a&gt;
that have been fixed as part of this release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Try it now!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please test it, try it out and report any issues back!
All being well 0.8.0RC1 will be released as 0.8.0 in a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;* Want to get involved in MongoEngine? We&amp;rsquo;re looking for help so please ping me!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automate all the things</title>
      <link>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/automate-all-the-things</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Ross Lawley</author>
      <guid>http://rosslawley.co.uk/posts/automate-all-the-things</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Disaster Strikes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week my Mac book ran out of space again, this had been going on for some time and I&amp;rsquo;d had enough.
I was spending an ever increasing amount of much time hunting down rogue space invaders on my small 120gb hard drive.  So &lt;strong&gt;something&lt;/strong&gt; had to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;text-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;In times like this there is only one solution!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/mrragequit.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Original image: http://leviathyn.com/games/news/2012/06/14/your-worst-rage-quit-moment/&#34; /&gt; &lt;br&gt;
    &lt;small&gt; Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://leviathyn.com/games/news/2012/06/14/your-worst-rage-quit-moment/&#34;/&gt;http://leviathyn.com/games/news/2012/06/14/your-worst-rage-quit-moment/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When upgrading to Mountain Lion I decided to start afresh and reformat my hard drive.
Normally starting from scratch would be a royal pain in the backside, taking many days to get things installed and allow me to get back to coding.
Then I remembered hearing about &lt;a href=&#34;http://boxen.github.com&#34;&gt;boxen&lt;/a&gt; which could give me an easy way to rebuild and &lt;em&gt;maintain&lt;/em&gt; the software on my Mac and hatched a plan of devops style automation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;My automation trifecta&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Boxen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boxen is built on top of &lt;a href=&#34;https://puppetlabs.com/&#34;&gt;puppet&lt;/a&gt; and it allows you to describe in code your Mac configuration and what software to install on it. To get started just copy githubs&amp;rsquo; starter &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/boxen/our-boxen&#34;&gt;boxen repo&lt;/a&gt; and then add your requirements.
I had to do two things to get my software stack automated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the main puppetfile link to the github sources and versions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my personal puppet manifest (modules/people/manifests/rozza.pp) include the classes for the software I want installed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit?!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it into github and run boxen. Volia a few minutes later my initial stack comprising; &lt;em&gt;Adium, Chrome, Dropbox, Intellij, Iterm2, Skype, Slate, Spotify, Sublime Text 2, Vagrant, Virtualbox, wget and Zsh&lt;/em&gt; were all installed and ready to use.
No wasting time hunting down .dmgs and navigating through their respective websites to download them.
If you want to know more about boxen then check out this &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/wfarr/boxen&#34;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt;.
All my configuration is now on github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rozza/my-boxen/&#34;&gt;my-boxen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;dotfiles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boxen is great as it automates the software installed on my mac but what about my general configuration? I could use Boxen and puppet to define and create &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my configuration files - but that seems unnecessarily complex and to me there is a separation of concerns. So when I asked on twitter what other folk do &lt;a href=&#34;http://intranation.com&#34;&gt;Brad Wright&lt;/a&gt; pointed me to his dotfiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a quick investigation I duly &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration:line-through;&#34;&gt;raided and plundered&lt;/span&gt; took inspiration from and now I have all my personal dot file configurations for things like &lt;em&gt;github, slate and zsh&lt;/em&gt; backed up on github.  What about private configuration files? Where it makes sense any files with a &lt;code&gt;.local_&lt;/code&gt; prefix will be sourced by their respective core configuration file.  That way I can have different configrations across machines - I can have a core &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; and a local version on each machine eg &lt;code&gt;.local_bashrc&lt;/code&gt;.  All my public &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rozza/dotfiles&#34;&gt;dotfiles&lt;/a&gt; are on github so plunder away!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Vagrant&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final piece in my automation puzzle is Vagrant.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been a huge fan of using vm&amp;rsquo;s for development for years and more recently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vagrantup.com/&#34;&gt;vagrant&lt;/a&gt; has been my tool of choice.
Installing things with apt-get on a linux vm just saves me time and pre-&lt;a href=&#34;http://10gen.com&#34;&gt;10gen&lt;/a&gt; my vms used to mirror my production environment.
As its a vm all I had to do is back it up before I wiped the hard drive and I could use that to get up and running
(I know its vagrant and had I been more diligent all I would have needed was the vagrant file and base box).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working on a vm, I still like to use sublime text on my mac to code.  So the way to achieve this is to nfs the code directory from the Mac into the vm - I used to do it the other way round, but having the code local to the mac makes editing very snappy.  The last thing to do was back up my code directory - I was surprised that all my checked out code weighs in at a hefty 13 gigs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Automation heaven&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;text-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/make-a-boxen.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;small&gt; Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/wfarr/boxen&#34;/&gt;https://speakerdeck.com/wfarr/boxen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using a combination of boxen, vagrant and dotfiles I massively reduced the time needed to rebuild my mac and get productive.
By backing up 13gb of source code, it meant I managed to reformat, install Mountain Lion and configure my Mac and get coding again in under 3 hours!
That included the time it took me to learn how to use boxen and setup dotfiles!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I will tweak those repositories overtime but all my core configuration for my Mac is now in a git repo on github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rozza/my-boxen/&#34;&gt;my-boxen&lt;/a&gt; for the software and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rozza/dotfiles&#34;&gt;dotfiles&lt;/a&gt; for configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m loving this adventure and if want to backup your software configuration or you&amp;rsquo;re getting a new Mac, then jump on board and automate all the things&amp;trade;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS&lt;/strong&gt;. Feel free to clone / copy my repo&amp;rsquo;s all I ask is if you add something cool you either comment below or &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/RossC0&#34;&gt;tweet me&lt;/a&gt; so I can use it to should I need to!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>